Finding Aid for Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity. Epsilon Chapter (University of Michigan) records 1909-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alpha Phi Alpha, Epsilon Chapter (University of Michigan) records
1909-2009
1978-1996
Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity. Epsilon Chapter (University of Michigan)
History, administrative records, topical files, and photographs largely relating to activities of Afro-American students at the University of Michigan.
88440 Bimu F47 2 UBImul F47
2 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group is on deposit from Alpha Phi Alpha, Epsilon Chapter, University of Michigan (Donor No. 7563 ).
The record group has been closed at the request of the fraternity. Individuals wanting access should contact either the current president or historian of the Epsilon Chapter. Written permission from one of these two individuals is required to examine the records.
Alpha Phi Alpha, Epsilon Chapter is an African American fraternity at the University of Michigan. Founded April 10, 1909, it is the fifth chapter in the history of Alpha Phi Alpha. The Epsilon Chapter has a history of community service, including tutoring, participating in the March of Dimes Walk/Run, and providing holiday baskets of food for needy local families. The chapter also sponsors many programs and speakers at the University of Michigan throughout the year. Some of the programs it has sponsored in the past include an annual tribute to Martin Luther King, Jr., a program helping to acclimate minority freshman students to the University of Michigan, and an annual event entitled A Salute to Black Women.
The Epsilon Chapter also has a special connection with the University of Michigan Angel Club. The Angel Club is non-Greek organization for African American women that was founded in 1982. The Angel Club and the Epsilon Chapter have a joint rush experience for their organizations at the beginning of the school year (called Gold Rush), host parties together, and perform community service projects together.
The records of Alpha Phi Alpha, Epsilon Chapter include information regarding the activities and experiences of African Americans at the University of Michigan, particularly during the 1920's, 1980's, and 1990's. Also a rich source of information about the history of the Epsilon Chapter, these records document the activities and administration of the Chapter, especially for the three decades previously mentioned. The records are divided into four series: History and Administrative Records, Topical Files, J. Leon Langhorne Papers, President's Papers and Centennial.
Subjects:
Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity. Epsilon Chapter (University of Michigan); African Americans--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.StudentsSocieties, etc.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1901-1910.StudentsSocial life and customs1901-1910.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.StudentsSocial life and customs1911-1920.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.StudentsSocial life and customs1921-1930.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1971-1980.StudentsSocial life and customs1971-1980.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1981-1990.StudentsSocial life and customs1981-1990.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1991-2000.StudentsSocial life and customs1991-2000.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--2001-2010.StudentsSocial life and customs2001-2010.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Minority college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Langhorne, J. Leon.
Subjects - Visual Material:
African American children--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African American students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African American women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity. Epsilon Chapter (University of Michigan); Basketball.; Fraternities and sororities.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.StudentsSocieties, etc.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.StudentsSocial life and customs1921-1930.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1981-1990.StudentsSocial life and customs1981-1990.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Sound Recordings
Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity. Epsilon Chapter (University of Michigan)
Contributors:
Langhorne, J. Leon.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- History and Administrative Records
  The first series, History and Administrative Records, contains early records of the fraternity, including an audio tape interview with one of the early members of the fraternity (J. Leon Langhorne) and a minute book (1909-1927). There are also records of the activities of the fraternity, including parties, workshops, and community service. Administrative and organizational records are contained in this group as well, including organizational charts, officers' reports, minutes of meetings, and several versions of the constitution and bylaws of the chapter. This series also contains a book by Charles H. Wesley, T he History of Alpha Phi Alpha: A Development in College Life, which is a general history of Alpha Phi Alpha from 1906 to 1979. Several references to the Epsilon Chapter and the University of Michigan are made in the book, many of which have been marked.
  - Audio Tape Recordings with J. Leon Langhorne, cassette (Box 1)
  - Early History (Box 1)
  - The History of Alpha Phi Alpha: A Development in College Life (10th and 13th editions.) 1961 and 1979, by Charles H.Wesley (Box 1)
  - Activities, 1981-1985 (Box 1)
  - Annual Ball, 1982-1988; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1978; 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and Memos, 1980-1986 (Box 1)
  - Minute Book, 1909-1927 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, Meetings, and Agendas, 1978-1984 (Box 1)
  - Organizational, 1981-1986 (Box 1)
  - Pledge Manual, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - President, 1979-1986 (Box 1)
    - Vice-President, 1980-1983 (Box 1)
    - Dean of Pledges, 1979-1984 (Box 1)
    - Committee and Officer's Reports, 1979-1985 (Box 1)
  - Rosters, 1974-1987 (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series primarily contains information dealing with minority student and "Greek" issues. There is also some information from the Theta Zeta Lambda Chapter of Alpha Phi Alpha, an Ann Arbor chapter of Alpha Phi Alpha that is closely connected with the Epsilon chapter.
  - Black Student Activities (Box 1)
  - Bursley Fashion Show, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - General "Greek" Material, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
  - Theta Zeta Lambda Chapter of Alpha Phi Alpha, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - 1983 (Box 1)
      (sheets from album)
    - Gary DeGuzman, circa 1985-1987 (Box 1)
    - Composite portraits of chapter members, 1911; 1929 (Folder UBImul F47)
- J. Leon Langhorne Papers
  The J. Leon Langhorne Papers series contains materials donated by J. Leon Langhorne, who became a member of the Epsilon Chapter in the 1920s. These materials include information about the early history of the Epsilon chapter, student life for African Americans at the University of Michigan in the 1920s, and some of the early members of Alpha Phi Alpha, including some of the founders of the fraternity. There are also a few photographs of Clarence W. Norris, whose writings about his experiences as an African American student at the University of Michigan (1923 to 1927) are contained in the Collected Papers folder of the series.
  - Collected Papers, 1911-1988 (Box 1)
    (includes autobiography of Clarence Wl Norris, Alpha Phi Alpha, UM, 1927)
  - Reminiscences, 1981-1986 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1926-1984 (Box 1)
- Presidents' Papers
  The Presidents' Papers series contains the papers of two presidents of the chapter: Sean Franklin and Ronald Jackson. The Sean Franklin Papers consist of an album of photographs showing some of the activities of the fraternity. The Ronald Jackson Papers include information on activities of the chapter, meetings, the president's reports, newspaper articles, and information about the Angel Club. There are also two photo albums containing photographs and other information about the various activities of the Epsilon chapter from 1993 to 1995.
  - Sean Franklin Papers
    - Photographs, circa 1993-1996 (Box 2)
  - Ronald Jackson Papers
    - History and Administrative Records
      - Activities, 1989-1996 (Box 2)
      - Angel Club, 1990-1992 (Box 2)
      - Calendar of Events, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
      - Constitution and By-Laws, 1987; 1995 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 2)
      - Historical Information (Box 2)
      - Meeting Agendas and Reports, 1990-1995 (Box 2)
      - Newspaper Articles, 1993-1996 (Box 2)
      - Organizational, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
      - Rosters, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
      - Theta Zeta Lambda Chapter, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Photographs
      - Photo Album, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
      - Photo Album, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
      - Loose Photographs from Album, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
- Centennial
  The Centennial series contains material relating to the centennial of the Alpha Phi Alpha Epsilon Chapter in 2009. Material includes a guest book, centennial meeting sign in sheets, souvenir journal, tickets and schedules, and oversize posters from an exhibit on Alpha Phi Alpha at the Harlan Hatcher Graduate Library. Some material collected at the centennial was added to the historical and administrative records series.
  - Centennial Meeting Sign-In Sheets, 2009 (Box 2)
  - Centennial Schedules and Tickets, 2009 (Box 2)
  - Centennial Souvenir Journal, 2009 (Box 2)
  - Guest Book, 2009 (Box 2)
  - Posters and Exhibit (Folder BImul F47)
  - Photographs
    - Alpha Phi Alpha House and Membership Card, 1950; circa 1952 (Box 2)
    - Chapter Members Group Photos, 1949-1951 (Box 2)
    - Inauguration of Zeta Delta (Michigan State) at Epsilon, 1948 (Box 2)
    - Interfraternity Sing, UM Hill Auditorium, May 10, 1950 (Box 2)